The second thing was apologizing. I had to apologize to the people I had hurt. Even though I had no expectations of them accepting it, it was important to do because it was the right thing. But I also had to apologize to myself. The third thing was atoning. For me, atoning meant going back into my community and working with at-risk youth who were on the same path, but also becoming at one with myself. Through my experience of being locked up, one of the things I discovered is this: the majority of men and women who are incarcerated are redeemable, and the fact is, 90 percent of the men and women who are incarcerated will at some point return to the community, and we have a role in determining what kind of men and women return to our community. My wish today is that we will embrace a more empathetic approach toward how we deal with mass incarceration, that we will do away with the lock-them-up-and-throw-away-the-key mentality, because it's proven it doesn't work. My journey is a unique journey, but it doesn't have to be that way. Anybody can have a transformation if we create the space for that to happen. So what I'm asking today is that you envision a world where men and women aren't held hostage to their pasts, where misdeeds and mistakes don't define you for the rest of your life. I think collectively, we can create that reality, and I hope you do too. Thank you. (Applause)
Lo segundo era pedir perdón. Tuve que pedirle perdón a la gente que había dañado. Aunque no tenía expectativas de que lo aceptaran, era importante hacerlo porque era lo correcto. Pero también tuve que pedirme perdón a mí mismo. Lo tercero era el resarcimiento. Para mí, eso significaba volver a mi comunidad a trabajar con jóvenes en riesgo que iban por el mismo camino, pero también reconciliarme conmigo mismo. Con la experiencia de estar encerrado, una de las cosas que descubrí es esta: la mayoría de los hombres y mujeres que están en la cárcel son recuperables. Y el hecho es que el 90 % de los hombres y mujeres que están en la cárcel en algún momento regresarán a la sociedad y somos responsables en determinar qué clase de hombres y mujeres vuelven a la sociedad. Hoy mi deseo es que tengamos una actitud más empática hacia el modo en que manejamos el encarcelamiento masivo, que nos deshagamos de esa mentalidad de "encerrarlos y tirar la llave", porque está comprobado que no funciona. El mío es un recorrido singular, pero no tiene que ser de ese modo. Cualquiera puede transformarse si generamos el espacio para que eso suceda. Lo que les estoy pidiendo hoy es que imaginen un mundo en el que hombres y mujeres no sean condenados por sus pasados, en el que los delitos y los errores no determinen el resto de una vida. Yo pienso que juntos podemos hacerlo realidad. Espero que Uds. también. Gracias. (Aplausos)